<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The addres [sic] of the University of St. Andrews to the King by the rector, vice-chancellor, heads of the colledges, deans of faculties and the rest of the masters and professors of the University of St. Andrews, whose names are insert at the end of their address; also a letter from the arch-bishops and bishops to the Kings Most Excellent Majesty.</title>
            <author>University of St. Andrews.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59543</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S297</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R33582</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13523821</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13523821</idno>
            <idno type="VID">99957</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A59543)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99957)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1556:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The addres [sic] of the University of St. Andrews to the King by the rector, vice-chancellor, heads of the colledges, deans of faculties and the rest of the masters and professors of the University of St. Andrews, whose names are insert at the end of their address; also a letter from the arch-bishops and bishops to the Kings Most Excellent Majesty.</title>
                  <author>University of St. Andrews.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.R. to be sold by A.L.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London:</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:99957:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99957:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ADDRES OF THE UNIVERSITY OF S<hi rend="sup">T</hi>. ANDREWS TO THE KING By the Rector, Vice-Chancellor, Heads of the Colledges, Deans of Faculties, and the reſt of the Maſters and Profeſſors of the Univerſity of St. <hi>Andrews,</hi> whoſe Names are inſert at the end of their Addreſs;</p>
            <p>ALSO, A Letter from the Arch-Biſhops, and Biſhops, to the Kings moſt Excellent Majeſty,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>J: R:</hi> to be ſold be <hi>A: L:</hi> 1689.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:99957:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:99957:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Rector, Vice-Chancellour, heads of the Colledges, Deans of Faculties and the reſt of the Maſters and Profeſſors of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity of <hi>St. ANDREWS.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">To the KING.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Univerſities and Seminaries of Learning have ſo great and peculiar a ſhare in the happy conſequence of the publick peace and Tranquillity, not only their flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing and increaſe, and your life and being, have ſuch a ſingular Dependance on the Supream Authority, that it cannot be juſtly either vanity or flattery when they endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to make their Gratitude as remarkable as their Advantages and Obligation; And we in this place do humbly offer to your <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty</hi> at this time, our moſt dutiful ſenſe and acknowledgments of the ſecurity, Peace, and Quiet we enjoy under the Wiſdom and Pater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal care of your Gracious and Happy Government.</p>
            <p>It was King <hi>James</hi> the firſt of that name, that founded this Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity the firſt in this Kingdom, and gave us theſe priviledges and immunities, which have been continued and enlarged by his Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Succeſſors; And we find by the frequent and ſignal marks of your Majeſties Princely care and concern for us, that you inherit with the Crown and Dignity of your Anceſtors the affection they bore to this Univerſity: And as we reflect on this gracious Tract of the Royal Favour to us, with the moſt grateful remembrance; ſo we cannot but alſo glory, that from the juſt notions of our duty and happineſs we have at all occaſions, and in the face of what ever hazards mantained an immoveable and affectionat Loyalty to the Government and adherance to the Royal Family.</p>
            <p>When by a happy providence this Nation was honored &amp; refreſhed with your Royal preſence, we chearfully concurred in the Land and Lively Joy and Acclamations of all Ranks of people in the univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:99957:3"/>Admiration of your Vertues that were ſo eminent, that your Enemies finding nothing elſe were forced to make Objections of them, and with our moſt ardent and ſincere wiſhes, for your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the peaceable poſſeſſion of the Throne and Empyre, to which (after your Royal Brother whom we ever remember with due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence and honour) the Laws of GOD, of Nature, and of theſe Kingdoms had eſtabliſhed your Right.</p>
            <p>And we owe the moſt profound and thankful Reverence to Heaven, which has been ſo favourable to the wiſhes of honeſt hearts, that we have a Prince of the Native and Royal Blood, to reign o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver us, who has given the moſt ſincere and ſolid demonſtrations of his love to theſe Kingdoms, by encounting the greateſt hazards for their Honour and Safety, who hath filled the World with the great and immortal Fame of his ſingular Accompliſhments in all the Acts and weighty concerns both of War and Peace, who ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding to that Gentle Innate Goodneſs, which has been very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable in his predeceſſors of this Royal Family, and having got (while he went himſelf through the rougheſt and moſt hazardous conditions of a Subject) a moſt tender ſenſe and feeling of our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities, does by the admirable effect of an incomparable Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency, to whatſoever offenders in principles or practices give the greateſt aſſurance of his being utterly averſe from the leaſt violence or ſeverity, even to the worſt of his Enemies, until it be extorted from his Royal Juſtice, and Magnanimity by obſtinate and inſufferable abuſes of his Benignity and Goodneſs; ſo that we cannot fancie what more is requiſite to the full and ſolid happineſs of people, but our juſt ſenſe of what we enjoy, and our firm relyance on your Majeſties faithfulneſs and generoſity to preſerve it inviolable.</p>
            <p>And we are ſure that your Majeſties loving Subjects who in the eye of the World, and the midſt not only of the noiſe and clamour of your Enemies, but alſo of your own reaſonable expectations, peaceably ſubmitted themſelves to your juſt poſſeſſion of your Crown, and Dominion, with ſolemn expreſſions of the greateſt joy and ſatisfaction, will never be guilty of a Levity, ſo abſurdly inconſequential to ſuffer themſelves to be diverted from their love and obedience, until they have ſhaken off all Tyes and Principles as well of Honour as of Duty.</p>
            <p>The ſad experience of our late Miſeries and convulſions has left
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:99957:3"/>us ſufficient marks and indications what rocks to ſhune, and has ſo diſgraced the Artifice and Deluſion of fears and jealouſies, that till we have loſt our Memories with our Judgements, it cannot be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected that the moſt Vulgar credulity can be wrought by that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſture. Theſe alone were the noyſome Vapours raiſed by wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs and ambition; and gathered into theſe clouds which dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Wiſdom and Glory of theſe Kingdoms, and ended in that fatal and dreadful ſtorm, which brought upon us all the heavy diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal calamities of Blood &amp; Confuſion. The pretended Fears of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary Government made us fight our ſelves Slaves to Arbitrary violence and oppreſſion, jealouſies created by malice, or blind and ſick imaginations of the hazard and change of Religion, produced the higheſt contempt of all that is Sacred, baniſhed all the vital and eſſential Characters of our peaceable and humble and moſt holy Faith, raiſed the moſt execrable Villanes on the ruines of One of the beſt and moſt Religious Kings, and made theſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms the ſchene of the moſt attrocious Villanies, and moſt diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable monſtruous barbarities that Hell could conſpire. And it is morally impoſſible Men can ever be ſure of any better conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence then diſorder and certain ruine from ſuch corrupt and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous cauſes, thoſe Viſions and Phantaſtick creatures of Sedition and Diſtempered Minds.</p>
            <p>Great Sir, We hope that this ſure and laſting Wiſdom which comes from the Obſervation of former misfortunes, that the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred tyes of our Religion and Reaſon with the love of our trueſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt will for ever produce the juſt and peaceable effects in the minds and endeavours of all your loving Subjects, and particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the Societies of Learning and Education who by their profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and opportunities are the Searchers of Truth, and are ſo cloſly knit to the publick ſafety, that in the time of inteſtine com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions they periſh, or are overcomed with Ignorance and barbari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and who therefore are guilty of an inexcuſable neglect and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude, if they ſlight or abuſe the Advantages they have of knowing and propagating the reaſonable principles of Love and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to your Majeſties ſacred perſon and Authority.</p>
            <p>The fundamental Rights of Government and Supremacy are ſo ſtronge and plain in Reaſon, and Divine Revelation, that they need not the weak and indecent aſſiſtance of Flattery, to ſupport or mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie them; They are alſo ſo Equable and Conſtant, and hold ſo
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:99957:4"/>unexchangeable under all lawful Soveraignes, never altering with Times and Circumſtances, and with all are of ſo great and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral importance, that it can never be unreaſonable, and ſo often neceſſary for honeſt Men to Declare and Aſſert them, and there may be as much indutyful malignity in affected and diſintended ſilence, as in malicious Grievances and Clamour.</p>
            <p>Sir, For theſe and the like conſiderations, it appears to us, your Majeſties Servants, in this your Ancient and Honourable Univerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, a neceſſary part of our duty, humbly to beg your Majeſties par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, and allowance, that we publiſh and Declare to the World, theſe clear diſtinct and certain Verities, which exact and deliberate Examination has fixed in our minds, concerning the Natural and perpetual Foundations of Society, Government, and Subjection, &amp; we reduce them ſhortly to theſe plain Propoſals &amp; Obſervations</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> As the Being, Nature, and whole Perfection of Mankind, are from GOD the Infinitely Perfect Being, and the Supream Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of all things; ſo there are ſome certain and fixed Methods and Means by which He will have theſe preſerved, and which He has given us ſufficient light to diſcover, and therefore whatſoever means are thus found to be abſolutely requiſire, for the Being and preſervation of Mankind, are for that reaſon of Divine Right, and Original, and are the Ordinance of GOD.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Of ſuch means it is evident that Society, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently Government, are the chiefeſt, for beſides that, the natural Order in which GOD has deſigned the preſervation of Mankind, is by the Poſterity and Succeſſion of one Generation to another, which it is hard to conceive poſſible, without Society the infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Humane Nature, and the neceſſities of our Life, are ſuch, that there are many things without which we cannot live; Which, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs, no Man that is alone and ſeparate from all others, can procure to himſelf. And as the Author of our Being, hath made this Society ſo neceſſar for preſerving us, He has alſo in ſeveral re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects fitted us for it, by implanting in our Nature a ſtrong inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to preſerve ourſelves; and in our Poſterity an earneſt deſire of Knowledge and Information, (not to ſpeak of the appetire of ſome) and which is moſt remarkable by affording us theſe Organs and Inſtruments of ſpeech &amp; Converſation, from all which put together, it is that the generality of Philoſophers, and Wryters concerning Government in all Ages, having called Man a Sociable Creature.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:99957:4"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> And as Mankind cannot ſubſiſt without Society, ſo neither can Society without Government, this is not only true in the matter of fact, and certain experience of all the World; but who ever conſiders humane nature, will neceſſarly ſee that it moſt be ſo. And that as man is partly fit, he is alſo partly unfit for Society, if every one were left to his own Liberty and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; the furious vehemency of contrare paſſions, the indelible love and eſteem of our ſelves above others: the unbanded deſires of many towards the ſame things, the weakneſs and puſilaminity of ſome compared with the ſtrength and ability of others; ſhould produce nothing better then unavoidable violence, rapine, fear, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and diſſolation: The very Speculative Suppoſition of which ſtate illuminates us fully to underſtand the abſolute neceſſity &amp; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable uſefulneſs of a power and authority, Superiour to every man and every faction of men, in the Society which may conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute and regulate every Mans Rights, Circumſcribe the Licentious Extenſions of mens Paſſions, and deſires to defend the Weak from the Injuries and Invaſions of the Stronger, puniſh the Tranſgreſſors of theſe Bands ſet on them. And in a word, may deliberate and do what ever may Contribute to the good and ſecurity of the whole Society, and of the whole parts of it, and it is the Power we call Government or Soveraignity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> As any Society ſhould quickly be deſtroyed, if every man in it were his own abſolute Governour, the ſame Reaſons de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate, that in one and the ſame Society, there cannot be a Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of diſtinct and Co-ordinate Governments for the ends above mentioned. For theſe ſhould be as abſurdlie lyable to the ſame inconveniencies, if not more and greater and as unpracticable as the ſingle Governments of every Man by himſelf: and tho in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very well ordered Society, their may and muſt be for the conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encies both of the Soveraign and the Subject ſome Inferiour ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate Powers, yet all theſe (that there be not a confuſed and endleſs Series of Subordination) moſt originally derive their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and duration from one that is Supream, and ſeeing there can be no Society preſerved, unleſs every man have his own will in it, and pleaſure abſolutely ſubjected to be Governed and Regulated by the Supreme and Soveraign, in all things which concern him, as a Member of that civil Corporation, then who ever goes about to plead Immunity from this Univerſal and Abſolute Subjection,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:99957:5"/>does upon the matter pleaſe the Society to be diſſolved, and ſo mankind to be deſtroyed, and conſequently he is to be conſidered as an enemy to Mankind, from all which it follows by the clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt light of Reaſon, that the Government and Soveraignity of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very formed State, and civil Society, is in its nature <hi>One indiviſible Supreme</hi> and <hi>Abſolute.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> There is nothing ſerves more to free us of the prejudices that ariſe in the Ignorant, or Inadvertent from the ſound of theſe Words, then diſtinctly to reflect and conſider, that this Suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of which we ſpeak, has been and is actually in all conſtituted Societies whatſoever: The diſtinctions of Monarchical and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular Authority, are not from the Nature of the Power it ſelf, but from the diverſities of the form, Subject or adminiſtration of it. The bigot <hi>Re-publicans</hi> cannot deny, but that the Plurality of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, or the Major part of them, in the Ancient <hi>Athenian,</hi> or ſuch other popular Eſtates, were all as Supream, Abſolute and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>controllable, as the <hi>Perſian, Aſſyrian,</hi> or whatſoever other Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie in the World; and every ſingle <hi>Athenian</hi> as Abſolutly ſubject as any ſingle Perſon or other <hi>Aſiatick.</hi> So that the Liberty of the Subject, is a meer empty name to amuſe and delude the Turbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and Unthinking Rable: and they needed no leſs then the higheſt Airie flouriſhes of the <hi>Roman</hi> or <hi>Grecian</hi> Rhetorick (which was ordinarly imployed in managnifing themſelves in every thing above all the World) to ſet of ſo manifeſt a contradiction, and who ever ſeriouſly conſiders the ſubſtantial grounds of all the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy contentions that have been in the World about Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſhall find that too many among them who know what they ſay, the queſtion is not if there is, or moſt be a Supreme and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Authority in every State, and civil Society; for that as it is neceſſary and unavoidable, ſo it is highly convenient, but in whoſe hands the Supremacie is (which is a thing the Seditious ever La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to perplex and obſcure) or with whom it may be left intruſted whither with one; or with a multitude, or Plurality, which are the differences of Form, we are in the natural Order to compare and examine in this place; it is fit to obſerve, that not only is the Supreme Power (as hath been ſaid) in it's own nature, <hi>One</hi> and <hi>Indiviſible,</hi> but in all States and civil Societies, it is lodged in one Perſon, either in a Natural or Moral ſenſe: For even in the more Popular parts, theſe many who are ſaid to have a ſhare in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:99957:5"/>have this power properly Lodged in them (according to the principles of the highſt <hi>Re-publicans</hi>) no otherwayes then as they are Morally, Civilly, or Virtually one, that is, as they aggree in one Mind, Will, or Determination. And therefore when we ſpeak of Government in the general, they as well as <hi>Monarchs,</hi> they may be called by one ſingle Name the Soveraign.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> We do the more fully comprehend the Nature of the Supreme Power and Soveraignity, by taking a diſtinct view of ſome of the moſt Conſiderable and Eſſential things that belong to it. And firſt, whoever has the Supreme Authority, is the Author and Pountain of all Civil Law and Juſtice: For to have the truſt and care of preſerving the Unity and Peace and Society of the whole and every part of the Society neceſſarly includes a Power of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberating, and judging what is fitteſt for theſe ends, of preſcribing theſe Rules, Meaſures, and directions, by which the Subjects (whoſe Wills as to theſe things that concern the Society, are ſubmitted to the Supreme) are in their ſeveral Capacities to Regulat their Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as alſo of fortefying theſe Laws againſt all contempt and diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and of puniſhing the Tranſgreſſors, ſeeing the moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Laws without being armed with the Coactive Strength and Authority ſhould be Naked, Ridicoulous, and Ineffectual: And whoever is the Supreme giver of the Laws, is for the ſame Reaſons Veſted with a Power to Interpret, Correct and change them as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie requires; Strict Riged, and Litteral Laws, is the Severeſt and Bloodieſt Maſter in the World: And therefore it belongs to the Supreme Power (in which is the Paternal care of the Subject) to Interpret and Mitigate the ſeverity of the Law, or ſuſpend its Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, as may beſt agree with the end of the publick ſafety, and the wholſome intention of all Laws whatſoever: The perpetual mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of new Actions, and qualities of Actions, which cannot be foreſeen: is ſo vaſt, that no Laws can be made ſo general, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſive as expreſly to comprehend them, and therefore it belongs to the Univerſal truſt &amp; care of the Supreme Power; there immediatly, or by inferior deputed Judges and Miniſtrators, not only to declare theſe Actions about which the Laws were directly intended, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to apply the general and material Juſtice of the Laws; to the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieties of Actions and Emergencies, which they cannot explicitly comprehend, the condition of Humane Affairs, the Tempers and Inclinations of the People, the means of advancing the moſt ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral eaſe and conveniences of the Government, and the Subject
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:99957:6"/>care remarkably Various &amp; Mutable; not only in different Nations and Societies, but at different times in one and the ſame; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the wiſeſt and celebrated Law Givers have acknowledged that their Laws were not the beſt they could have framed, but only the beſt the condition of their People could bear at the time of their making; and were therefore, with the alteration of their condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and circumſtances to be Rectified or Improven: Yea, even theſe Laws which the <hi>Sacred Hiſtory</hi> tells us, were conveyed by <hi>Moſes</hi> from GOD himſelf to the <hi>Jewiſh Nation,</hi> cannot be ſaid to be the moſt compleat and perfect Directions that could be given to Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind: otherways all the World, at leaſt ſuch as heard of them, ſhould indiſpenſably be oblidged to their Obſervation, but their perfection conſiſted in their being Proportionated and adopted to the Capacity, Temper, and Circumſtances of that Rude, Ignorant, Supperſtitious, Unthankful and Senſual People, for whole Benefit they were given. Aand when the Obſervation of theſe Laws and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies were deſigned, to ſeparate and diſtinguiſh from the Luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and corrupted Nations. And ſo for the alteration of Times and Circumſtances, and the Diminution of the Hazards againſt which they were intended: Some of the moſt Conſiderable of them, were innocently diſpenſed with, and is continued: and at laſt, the whole or Genetality abrogated and louſed their Obligation from all which it is evident, that generally ſpeaking an immutable Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Law, is an abſurdity or contradiction, and when ever former Laws and Conſtitutions appear to the Supreme Power, (who is the only Judge in ſuch Caſes) to fail of their Subſerviencie to the more general Happineſs and Conveniencies of the Society; the Soveraign has not only unqueſtionable Right, but is found by the nature of ſupream Power and Truſt, which is from the Gracious and the bountiful Governour of the World, to Alter, Correct, or Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogate them as may be moſt expedient. <hi>2dly.</hi> The Soveraign to whom belongs the Care, not only of the Internal Order and Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of the Society, but alſo of the ſecuring of it from External Violence, and preſerving its Ballance and Proportion with the Neighbouring States and Societies, has the undoubted power of making War and Peace; and conſequently of the raiſing and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of Forces, making Confederacies, ſending Ambaſſadours, keeping Correſpondences, and preſcribing the neceſſar Expences, affoorded by the Subjects, for theſe and other Neceſſities of the Government; and for the ſupporting the Strength, Honour and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:99957:6"/>Intereſt of the Nation. <hi>3dly.</hi> And it belongs to the Soveraign on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, (in whom is the Supremacie and Original Jurisdiction, and whoſe it is to Judge of the Qulifications and Fitneſs of ſuch as may be imployed in any inferiour Adminiſtration) to Errect and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulate the Freedoms and Priviledges of all inferiour Corporations, to Conſtitute <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> to Appoint and Nominate all publick Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, Officers of State, Judges, Counſellours; and in a word, all that ſerve in any Publick Civil Truſt, &amp; Capacity whatſoever.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seventhly,</hi> Theſe are the Foundamental and Vital <hi>Prerogatives</hi> of Government and Supremacy, to which all the other Particulars by Conſequence and Connexion are eaſily Reduceable: And now from what has been ſaid in the General concern of Government, the inference is Natural and Obvious, that whoſoever murmurs againſt the Being or Exerciſe of the Supream Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, who abſurdly pretends to limit it, for ſome ſeeming preſent advantage endeavour to incroach upon the <hi>Prerogative</hi> of the right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Soveraign, is guilty not only of the greateſt wickedneſs, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temning the Power, and reſiſting the <hi>Ordinance of God,</hi> but alſo of the greateſt Folly, by doing what in him lyes, to ſubvert the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of all Peace and Tranquillity, and to ſhake and unſettle that <hi>ſureſt Rock</hi> on which his own, and his poſterities perpetual ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and happineſs is built.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eightly,</hi> As to the different Forms of Government, it may be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved: firſt, that ſeeing no man denyes, but that it is poſſible in any Society, to have it ſufficiently known, and publickly acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, what is their form of Government, or in whoſe hands the Soveraignity is Lodged; it is certain that that Society, is in ſo far the happieſt of all others in which this is moſt Diſtinctly and Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally known. <hi>2dly.</hi> When we are inquiring into the beſt form of Government, is not to be expected that any one can be found which is abſolutly perfect, for in this our frame and imperfect State, it is impoſſible to find any humane Adminiſtration that is attended with no inconveniencie or imperfection, but by the moſt perfect Government in this State of things, we are to underſtand that which is lyable to the feweſt inconveniencies, and from which the moſt advantage and the more ſolid, and permanent can be juſtly expected to the Society.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ninthly,</hi> And ſo, tho we are not raſhly or dogmaticaly, to condemn the ancient and eſtabliſhed Government of any Nation by which
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:99957:7"/>it has enjoyed its ſecurity, yet we cannot be ſo blind, as not to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand that of all the ſeveral forms of Government which the witt or ſubtility of man can imagine the <hi>Monarchical,</hi> that is, where the Soveraiguty is lodged in one ſingle perſon, in the natural ſenſe is evidently lyable to the feweſt and ſmalleſt inconveniencies and is moſt exactly proportionated for the attaining and preſerving the Peace and Security, and all the other ends of Society and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, when we conſider; firſt, that it is the moſt natural Being, the Modal and Draught of the Paternal or Patriarchicall Power, from which it has its Original. In the conſtituted Order of the World, Men are not dropt down from the clouds, but Born and Educated in ſome Family, and Society, which thing is enough to deſtroy the vain preſence of the natural Liberty, and equality of all men, from the ſubjection of the Children to their Parents, from whom they have their Being &amp; by whom they are Preſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and Educated, is ſo clear <hi>by the light of Nature,</hi> and has been ſo uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally acknowledged by all Nations and People; that it were but a loſs of time to prove it in the particulars. And it being alſo certain from the moſt Ancient Authors that all the Primitive Governours were <hi>Paternal</hi> and <hi>Monarchical;</hi> Kingdoms then being nothing elſe but larger, and more extended Families has given oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to the later Authors to obſerve, that all Governments by <hi>plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality,</hi> as they are in themſelves unnatural, ſo they appear from the Hiſtorie to have had their Beginning from ſome <hi>odd and mutable change,</hi> or from moſt unjuſt <hi>uſurpation</hi> and <hi>violence.</hi> But then, <hi>2dly,</hi> not to inſiſt in reſembling <hi>Monarchy</hi> to the <hi>Supreame Providence</hi> and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the World, or in illuſtrating the Argument of moſt part of all <hi>Divines,</hi> to prove the <hi>unity of the Deitie</hi> from <hi>Its Being,</hi> uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveable, how there can be two or moe ſupream Governours of all things; there ſeems to be in all <hi>pluralities</hi> of <hi>Humane Governours</hi> a fatal neceſſity and perpetual natural occaſion of Faction and Diviſion, things directly oppoſite to all the good Deſigns of Laws, Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Society, it being next too impoſſible, but that among many equal ſharers of Authority, there will be always ſome who are acted by partial Intereſt, ſome by Ambition, and the Emola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Rivals, ſome by a vanity of ſhewing their Parts, ſome by an uneaſie pride and ſingularity, and tho there were no thing elſe, the diverſity of Opinions which is unavoidable, is able to produce Jealouſies, Envy, and Animoſities; and theſe are able to weaken, embroyl, or diſturb any Society. <hi>3dly,</hi> In a plurality any
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:99957:7"/>one that is diſaffected to a Deſign, if he have ſenſe or a <hi>little popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larity,</hi> can create more difficulties and delayes then many are able to anſwer or overcome; &amp; the juſt opportunity of doing <hi>publick affairs</hi> are often loſt by their contentions &amp; <hi>tedious conſultations,</hi> and even when they come to a concluſion, it happens frequently that (as ſome of the <hi>Ancients</hi> were wont to rail the <hi>Athenian Councils,</hi> tho wiſe men conſult and deliberat, fools and mad men determine. <hi>4hly,</hi> In a multitude of Governours the publick is neglected fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, whiles any ſingle man thinks himſelf but little concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and that he will be blamed for the Errors of the Government; and theſe who are more active, and have been eſteemed the wiſeſt men in ſuch Governments, have alwayes endeavoured to gain Reputation to their Councils, by being ſupported by the popular favour: And by what mean and unworthy Arts that is procured, and when attainted, how light and inconſtant it is all the World knows. <hi>5ly,</hi> Secrecie which is a thing undoubtedly requiſite, for the ſafety and expedition of publick Councils, is very rare, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt impoſſible in a <hi>Plurality. 6ly,</hi> A <hi>Monarchical Government,</hi> be cauſe it is free of theſe, and the like heavy inconveniencies, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is caſier to find a good and wiſeman, then many, becauſe the Vulgar which is always the greateſt part of any <hi>multitude</hi> or <hi>plurality,</hi> is ever ignorant, raſh, and untractable, and becauſe of the manifold advantages of this Government, it has been always thought in all Ages and Nations, abſolutely neceſſar in Armies; and the ſame reaſons hold as naturaly, and clearly in <hi>Civil Societies.</hi> And therefore it is no wonder that <hi>Monarchs</hi> have been more ſolid, and permanent, and of far longer duration then <hi>Popular Governments,</hi> and their Subjects more univerſally pleaſed under the exerciſe of their Authority.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tenthly,</hi> That thoſe inconveniencies of Government by plurality are not airly ſpeculations will be clear to any who ſeriouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiders the miſerable face of that <hi>Republick,</hi> which by the Admirers of Popular Government was ſet up as the greateſt beloved Idol, for when we ſee that after the moſt unjuſt expulſion of the <hi>Roman Kings,</hi> the <hi>Conſuls</hi> uſurped their <hi>Authority,</hi> and carried it higher than ever they did, that the <hi>Tribunies</hi> theſe <hi>Incendiaries of the Rable,</hi> when they had got their Being, and a little footing, managed a continual de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, ſparing no <hi>Artifice</hi> or violence to diminiſh the <hi>conſular Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> as being to <hi>Arbitrary</hi> and <hi>Tyrannical;</hi> and to get it into their own
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:99957:8"/>hands (in which they became by deſires more and more ſuccesful) on pretence of giving it to the People, that during the more ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly Popular form of Government, never were their greater roar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and complaints of Oppreſſion, in any ſtate of the World, that the conſtant Diſcentions betwixt the Nobility and the People pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced perpetual Tumults, where the Streets were filled with the Blood and Gore of their Citizens, and all places with the ſad Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities of Civil War and Confuſion. And when we conſider that in all their greateſt hazards and difficulties, they were found to run to the expedient of a <hi>Monarchical Dictator;</hi> And that (as all their Authors Confeſſes) they had been at laſt utterly deſtroyed and ſunk under their civil Calamities, if they had not again fallen under a laſting <hi>Monarchical Government:</hi> Theſe are ſufficient demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, when People Sacrilegiouſly encroach on the Right of their lawful Superiours. It is hard for them ever to fix on any thing of ſolid duration, that the famous <hi>Roman Libertie,</hi> was properly but an Impunity for cutting one anothers Throats, that Faction and Diſorder, which all the wiſdom &amp; ſtrength of that people could not prevent, all the natural effects of ſuch Governments; and that the happineſs of a State conſiſts, not in the Greatneſs and Extent of its Bounds and Empire, but in its Internal order and Tranquillity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eleventhly,</hi> As to the great publick inconveniencies of a <hi>Monarchs</hi> turning a Tyrant. It is obſervable, Firſt, That the marks of a Tyrant are ſo variouſly and dubiouſly given by the enemies of Monarchy, that it is very hard for the moſt Ingenious, much more for the Vulgar to determine, where any Governour deſerves this odious Character. <hi>2dly,</hi> If every man would induſtriouſly imploy himſelf in the proper buſineſs of his own calling and capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, there would be little time and leſs occaſion, for theſe unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable Inquiries into the Councils and Actions of <hi>Princes;</hi> which of neceſſity, muſt be kept more cloſs and myſterious then theſe of private men: And yet we ſee how lyable theſe are to be often and greatly miſrepreſented. <hi>3dly,</hi> Tho there is no ſhadow of true rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, to imagine that <hi>Monarchs</hi> are accomptable to their Subjects for their Adminiſtration, which is an Errour no leſs abſurd (an accomptable <hi>Monarch,</hi> being an inferior Supreme,) then it is perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious both in Government and Religion; Yet Princes cannot but remember, that as Subjects are accountable to their Soveraign, and Superior: So Monarchs are to theirs, the Great GOD and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:99957:8"/>Governour of the World, by whom Kings reign; and againſt whom only they ſin. <hi>4ly,</hi> We cannot fancy very few Monarchs ſo void of common ſenſe, as not to underſtand that their Honour and ſafty does depend on the happineſs and proſperity of their Subjects, ſo it is next too impoſſible that they can deſign their general hurt and oppreſſion. <hi>5ly,</hi> When ſome Severities actually happen which are generally lookt upon as exceſſes of Government, they are never ſo heavy in Nature, nor ſo Univerſal in their Extent and Duration, as the dreadful Calamities of <hi>Civil War,</hi> which is the common cauſe of the frailtie and mortality of <hi>Empires;</hi> and which is thus always ſo unluckie as to produce the ſame, and more, and greater Evils then are pretended to be feared or ſuffered from the Lawful Superior; and whoever by his fears, diſcontents, and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, will needs diſturb the Government or would circumſcribe it muſt aſurdly ſuſpect himſelf to a power which he muſt acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, to be greater, otherways he cannot dream how he can ſet Limits to the former. But laſtly, which is a ſufficient anſwer, when it is asked what if a Monatch abuſe the Power, neglect the dictates, or Laws of his Kingdom; we ask the enemies of Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie, what if in their forms of Government, the Major part or Reſpreſentatives and Truſties of the People do the ſame? If they ſay, that theſe can be reſiſted or judged by the reſt, then it ſeems very evident, that there can be no Government at all, or at leaſt none that can be promiſed to be of a weeks continuance, if theſe cannot be juſtly oppoſed or reſiſted, then it is clear that the difficultie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, is at leaſt equal in all forms of Government; but that it is greater on the <hi>Re-publicans</hi> ſide, we are able to bring from impartial Hiſtory, many more example of Popular Governments, generaly vitiated, or in which avaritious, irreligious, and licentious Men, have had the whole ſwey, then can be produced of wicked Monarchs: And this one matter of Fact being true, is enough to deſtroy all the empty Objections of the Enemies of Monarchie; as to that caſe of the Alteration of Civil Laws, beſides that theſe have no force, nor obligation, but what they intirely derive from the Soveraign. And we are by all the Rules of Diſcretion and Charity, to ſuppoſe that when ever there happens any change in any of them, it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for the better, and for the more general convenience, of which the Soveraign always is Judge; who ever thinks the perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuity of Laws an advantage to a State or Society, moſt have the leſs eſteem of Popular Government, when after examination ye
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:99957:9"/>ſhall find that never was there a greater number of partial and ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous conſtitutions, never more frequent abrogations, viciſſrudes, and changes of Laws, then in the <hi>Roman, Athenian,</hi> and ſuch other Republicks, which has given occaſion to that remark of ſome La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyers: That any conſiderable alteration in the Civil Laws cannot be expected in Monarchies, in leſs then the Revolution of 30 years, generally ſpeaking, but in the Popular Governments, with every Callends of <hi>January.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Twelfthly,</hi> From what has been ſaid in the general concerning Monarchy it is eaſie to obſerve, that theſe Monarchies are moſt perfect which are <hi>Hereditary,</hi> Being in their Nature, of the moſt equable Stability, for ſeeing every Succeſſor in ſuch a Series, has a full right to the intire Soveraignity: This Right can never pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe or be diminiſhed. And tho the Wiſdom of the moſt Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Monarchies, is in all Ages, thought to uſe ſeveral Methods and Forms of Conſulting their Subjects in the great and weighty Affairs of the Government, yet no Conceſſion whatſoever to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, no cuſtom be it never ſo long of imploying them, or any num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of them, for private or more ſolemn Counſels, or in adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Juſtice, can Allienat any part, or making any ſhares of the Supreme Authority, the Society may alſo Reaſonably expect the greateſt care and ſincereſt love from <hi>Hereditary Princes,</hi> who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the Government and Society, as their Property and Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance will watch over it, with the more dilligent and circumſpect exactneſs, that they may tranſmit it in the more ſecure and flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing condition to their poſterity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thriteenthly,</hi> And now in the laſt place, what is the fixed and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed Government of this ancient Kingdom, we cannot ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain or aſſert in words more clear and comprehenſive then theſe. In which at ſeveral times and different occaſions, the Subjects of this Realm have ſolemnly ſworn, either inviolable fidelity and allegiance, and in which the Repreſentatives of the Body of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in their moſt ſolemn and lawful Convocations, have openly declared to the World the unqueſtionable Rights of this <hi>Monorchical Government;</hi> in theſe it is ſolemnly owned and acknowledged, (for Subjects give no Prerogative but aſſert them) in ſeveral publick Oaths and Declarations, that the Kings Majeſty is the alone Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Governour of this Kingdom, and above all Perſons in it whatſomever; that he is a free Prince of a Soveraign Power, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:99957:9"/>as great Liberties and Prerogatives as any other King, Prince, or Potentate whatſomever; that his Majeſty is a Soveraign Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch, Abſolute Prince, Judge and Governour over all Perſons, Eſtates and Cauſes, in this Realm: That the Kings ſacred Majeſty and his Heirs, and Succeſſors, for ever, hold the Royal Power from <hi>God Almighty</hi> over this Kingdom. And that there are great Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations from the Laws of GOD, the Laws of Nations, the Munici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Laws of the Land, and Oath of Allegiance to maintain and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the Soveraign Power and Authoritie of the Kings <hi>Majeſty,</hi> and that ſad conſequences do accompany any incroachments upon or diminitions thereof; they acknowledge the great happineſs that this Kingdom hath for many Ages enjoyed under the Princely Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their Royal Kings, who by the ſpecial bleſſing of <hi>Almighty God</hi> have reigned over them, in ſo long and unparalelled a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Royal Diſcents, and the Obligations thereby lying on them in Conſcience, Honour and Gratitude, to own and aſſert the <hi>Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Prerogatives</hi> of the Imperial Crown of this Kingdom, which the Kings Majeſty holds from <hi>God Almighty</hi> alone; and to vindicate the ſame from all Invaſions made upon it, that all Government and Juriſdiction within his Majeſties Ancient Kingdom, does Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginally recide in his Sacred Majeſtys Lawful Heirs &amp; Succeſſors, and it being impoſſible to invent any ſurer way of knowing the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of any Kingdom, who e're <hi>impartially</hi> conſiders theſe with many ſuch other Declarations, whereof, ſome have been made when any doubt aroſe concerning any particular of the Royal Prerogatives; and ſome after a ſad experience of the fatal conſequences of Sacrile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Invaſions upon them, and all to expreſs the publick ſenſe of the Nation, concerning the rights of their Sacred Soveraign: Who ever, take notice, that our Kings have ever been the Fountain of Civil Juſtice, making Laws of Univerſal unqueſtioned Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion on all the Subjects; ſometimes by themſelves alone, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time by the Advice and conſent of their <hi>Barrons;</hi> ſometimes of their <hi>Earls;</hi> ſometimes of their <hi>Prelats;</hi> and ſometimes of their <hi>Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentatives</hi> of the Generality of their Subjects, which have been aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled by their Authority; and are in theſe Laws frequently called their great Council or Parliament. And in a Word, who ever conſiders the whole threed of our free and unbayſed Hiſtory, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but be convinced, how clear and certain it is (if it be poſſible for words clearly to expreſs any thing) That this ancient Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:99957:10"/>is properly <hi>Monarchical.</hi> And that in the Sacred Perſon of our King is lodged, the <hi>Supreme Power</hi> and <hi>Authority;</hi> with all theſe inviolable Rights and Prerogatives, which belongs to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire <hi>Soveraignity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourtenthly,</hi> In <hi>Buchannan</hi> (who has been juſtly called a reproach, as well as any Ornament of our Country,) we admire the empty looſnes of his reaſoning, no leſs then we do the purity of his <hi>Latine,</hi> his frothie Dialogue, is an inſtance how farr Malice, Paſſion, and miſtaken intereſt, can lead men out of the common Rod of ſenſe and reaſon; his Characters of a King, and of a Tyrant, are ſo Chimerical and Imaginarie, and with all, ſo nyce and poſſitive, that according to his diſcriptions, there were never King or Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant in the World. But in ſhort, if his intended paralel of a King and Phyſician, be in many things impertinent, if it be inconſiſtant that his King be ſometimes the perfecteſt thing in the World, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therways to be reſiſted or expelled, and ſometimes very imperfect, that he may get Laws to govern him, juſt as the <hi>Latine,</hi> and the <hi>Rapture</hi> takes the Author, if he is blindly in Love with the word <hi>Laws,</hi> without conſidering the thing who ſhall make them; if it do not follow that becauſe ſome Kings have been Ill men, therefore there ſhould be no King: Or if the ſame reaſon hold in the <hi>Popular Government,</hi> and if there have been at leaſt as many and great cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions in <hi>Popular Governments</hi> as in <hi>Monarchies,</hi> which are things any can demonſtrate, who are not ſtrangers to Reaſon and Hiſtory: Then all theſe <hi>Rhetorical Floriſhes</hi> which makes up this <hi>Authors</hi> Book about Government, (which hath abuſed ſome whoſe conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons go not beyond the ſurfice of things,) do conclude nothing but that if he had beſtowed a little of that time which he ſpent in ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring of <hi>Language,</hi> on the ſtudy either of <hi>Law</hi> or <hi>Geometry,</hi> he might have Learned to purſue this malicious deſign, a little more cloſly, while as now he hath only made it appear that he was cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to write a Play; but not either Law or Reaſon concerning Government.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>SIR,</hi> Theſe Aſſertions and Obſervations are owned by the whole Body of this Univerſity, ſince they ſeem to be founded on clear Methedical and Permanent Reaſons. If they do not diſpleaſe your <hi>Majeſty,</hi> we ſhall be carefull to inſert them in our moſt Solemn Records, to remain as a perpetual Monument of the unalterable Principles of this <hi>Society.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:99957:10"/>
            <p> We do not offer to your <hi>Majeſty,</hi> without the ſpecial Approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the moſt <hi>Reverend Chancellor</hi> of this Univerſity, the great and happy Influence of whoſe Example and Council, on the <hi>Loyalty</hi> &amp; Order of this Place, is ſutable to the geeatneſs of his Truſt &amp; In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in it: We ſhall rejoyce in our happineſs, if what we have ſaid, can do any ſervice to Diſſipate the clouds of Ignorance or Prejudice, that are on the minds of any who have not leaſure or advantages of long and Laborious Inquiries, into the Reaſonable Foundation of their Allegience; there being nothing dearer to us, then the Fidelity and Affection we bear to the moſt Ancient and Royal <hi>Government</hi> of this Kingdom, and to your <hi>Majeſties ſacred Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> who is the breath of our Noſtirls, and who has been graciouſly pleaſed, to take the State of your Univerſities among the firſt and principal Concerns of Your Government, and who, we do not doubt, will continue, to confirm and enlarge with Your Empire the Learned Glory of Your Kingdoms. And we dare with the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cereſt boldneſs of our honeſt Hearts, aſſure Your <hi>Majeſty,</hi> that the juſt and never unfaſhionable Notions of our Duty, with the intire Truſt and Confidence, we repoſe in Your <hi>Majeſty,</hi> ſhall ever pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve us from being diverted, or frighted from our Love and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and ſhall excite from Your <hi>Majeſty,</hi> and Kingdoms happineſs, the perpetual Prayers of, &amp;c.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Signed by</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Arthur</hi> Arch-biſhop, <hi>Chancellor</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Alexander Skeen</hi> Vice-chancellor</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Richard Waddel</hi> Arch-deacon</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>James Lorimer</hi> D. D.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>All Regents.</head>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Charles Kinnard</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Menzies</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Alexander Skeen</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Patrick Mcgill</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>William Comery</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>James Roſs</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Monro.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>A LETTER From the Arch-biſhops and Biſhops, to the King's moſt Excellent <hi>Majeſty.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <hi>May it pleaſe Your moſt Sacred</hi> Majeſty,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WE proſtrate our ſelves to pay our moſt Devoute Thanks and Adoration to the Soveraign Majeſty of Heaven and Earth, for preſerving Your Sacred Life and Perſon, ſo frequently expoſed to the greateſt hazards, and as often
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:99957:11"/>delivered, and you miraculonſly proſpered with Glory and Victory, in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the Rights and Honour of Your Majeſties Auguſt Brother, and of theſe Kingdoms; and that by his Merciful Goodneſs, the Ragings of the Sea, and madneſs of unreaſonable Men, have been ſtilled and calmed; Your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty as the Darling of Heaven, peaceably ſeated on the Thrones of Your Royal Anceſtors, whoſe Long, Fluſtrious, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nparallelled Line, is the greateſt glory of this Your Ancient Kingdom.</p>
            <p>We pay our moſt humble gratitude to Your Majeſty, for the Repeating Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances of Rour Yoyal Protection to our National Church and Religion, as the Laws have Eſtabliſhed them; Which are very ſuitable to the Gracious Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, Encouragement and protection, Your Majeſty was pleaſed to afford to our Church and Order, whilſt we were happy in Your preſence amongſt us.</p>
            <p>We Magnifie the Divine Mercy in bleſſing Your Majeſty with a SON, and us with a PRINCE, whom we pray Heaven may bleſs and preſerve to ſway Your Royal Seepters after you, and that he may Inherit with Your Dominions, the Illuſtrious and Heroick Vertues of his Auguſt and moſt Serene parents.</p>
            <p>We are amazed to hear of the Danger of an Invaſion from <hi>Holland,</hi> which excites our prayers for an univerſal repentance to all Orders of Men, that God may yet ſpare his people, preſerve your Royal perſon, and prevent the Effuſion of Chriſtian Bloods, and to give ſuch ſucceſs to your Majeſties Arms, that all who Invade your Majeſties Juſt and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndoubted Rights, and Diſturb or inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt the peace of your Realms, may be Diſappointed and clothed with ſhame, ſo that on your Royal Head the Crown may ſtill flouriſh.</p>
            <p>As by the Grace of God we ſhall preſerve in our ſelves a firm and unſhaken Loyalty, ſo we ſhall be careful and zealous to promote in all your Subjects: an Intemerable and ſtedfaſt Allegiance to your Majeſty, as an Eſſential Part of their Religion, and of the Glory of our Holy profeſſion; not doubting but that God in his great mercy, who hath ſo often preſerved and delivered your Majeſty, will ſtill preſerve and deliver You by giving You the Hearts of your Subjects, and the Necks of your Enemies. So pray we, who in all Humility, are,</p>
            <p>May it pleaſe your moſt Sacred Majeſty, your Majeſties moſt Humble, moſt Faithful, and moſt Obedient Subjects and Servants,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Edinburgh. <date>Nov. <hi>3. 1688.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Signed by
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Arch: St: And:</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Jo. Glaſgow.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Alexr: Edinburgen:</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Jo: Galloviden:</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Jo: Dunkelden:</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Gec: Abredonen:</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Will: Moravien:</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ja: Roſſen:</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ja: Brichen:</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ro: Dumblanen:</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Arch: Sodoren:</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>And: Orcaden:</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:99957:11"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
